Finding Aid for the John Egerton Papers, Addition
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John Egerton Papers, Addition
2014
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0695
5.01 linear feet
Biographical Sketch
John Edgerton was born in Atlanta, Georgia, June 14, 1935, the son of William G. Egerton, a traveling salesman, and his wife, Rebecca White Egerton. The family soon settled in Cadiz, Kentucky, where John Egerton remained until leaving to attend Western Kentucky University, 1953-1954. From 1954 until 1956, he served in the United States Army. He earned a B.A. at the University of Kentucky in 1958 and an M.A. in 1960. In 1957 he married Ann Elizabeth Bleidt, the couple have two sons.
Between 1958 and 1960, Egerton was with the Public Relations Department of the University of Kentucky, and from 1960 to 1965, he was the Director of Public Information for the University of South Florida. He was a staff writer for Southern Education Report, 1965-1969, and for Race Relations Reporter, 1969-1971.
In 1971, Egerton began his career as a free-lance reporter. He was a contributing editor for Saturday Review of Education (1972-1973), Race Relations Reporter (1973-1974), and Southern Voices (1974-1975). From 1973-1975, he was a writer for Atlanta’s Southern Regional Council. In 1977-1978, he was journalist-in-residence at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Egerton has written or edited eleven non-fiction books and contributed over two hundred articles to periodicals. He has also been a participant in and writer for many projects or conferences dealing with desegregation and civil rights.
Scope and Content Note
Most of this addition to John Egerton Papers (MSS128) consists of freelance articles Egerton wrote between 1966 and 2006. There are also additional materials relating to his books: A Mind to Stay Here (1970); The Americanization of Dixie (1973); and Nashville: The Faces of Two Centuries (1979). Other materials include speeches, book reviews, and planning for Nashville’s first Southern Festival of Books.
- Box Listing
  - A Mind to Stay Here, (1970)
    - Research Notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Publication Notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Incoming, A-C (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Incoming, D-W (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Contract and Royalty Statements (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reviews (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Reviews (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Americanization of Dixie, (1973)
    - Pages 1-35 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pages 36-61 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pages 62-83 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Pages 84-111 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Pages 112-135 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Pages 136-158 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Pages 159-179 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pages 180-216 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Pages 217-226 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Nashville: The Faces of Two Centuries, (1979)
    - Foreword Material (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - A, 1-27 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - B, 1-35 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - C, 1-32 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - D, 1-27A (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - D, Warren, 1-3724. E, 1-41 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Word Pictures, A, 1-38 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Word Pictures, B, 1-32 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Word Pictures, C, 1-23 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Word Pictures, D, 1-27 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Word Pictures, E, 1-18 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Galley Proofs for Nashville: The Faces of Two Centuries are in Box 89 of John Egerton Papers (MSS 128) (Box 2)
  - Southern Festival Of Books---Correspondence, Incoming---Alexander-Woodward (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Southern Festival of Books---Correspondence Outgoing, August 3, 1986-April 4, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Southern Festival of Books, 1989---Planning Materials (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Southern Festival of Books, 1989---Planning Materials (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Southern Festival of Books---Publicity and Author Biographies (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Southern Festival of Books, 1989---Reviews (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Southern Festival of Books, 1990---Correspondence-Incoming---Cheatham-McCash (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Southern Festival of Books---Planning (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Avon Williams, Jr. Tribute, 1994---Correspondence-Incoming---Dinkins-Williams (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Avon Williams, Jr. Tribute, 1994---Correspondence-Outgoing, June, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Avon Williams, Jr. Tribute, 1994---Research (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Avon Williams, Jr. Tribute---Tributes for Memorial Service, 1994 and 63rd Birthday Celebration, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - John Maguire Project (Democracy/Race/Culture/), 1998-2001---Correspondence-Incoming---Maguire, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - John Maguire Project---Correspondence-Incoming---Maguire, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - John Maguire Project---Correspondence-Incoming---Maguire, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - John Maguire Project---Correspondence-Outgoing, June 2, 1999-November 20, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - John Maguire Project---Participants (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - John Maguire Project---Publications---Tool Kit---English (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - John Maguire Project---Publications---Tool Kit---Spanish (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - John Maguire Project---Publications---Tool Kit---Tagalog (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - John Maguire Project---Publications---Tool Kit---Vietnamese (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - John Maguire Project---Publications---Tool Kit---Chinese (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - John Maguire Project---Publications---Tool Kit---Korean (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Freelance Articles, 1966-2006 (A note attached to these papers states that most freelance articles from the 1990s on are on floppy discs.) (Box 3)
  - Alice Lloyd-The College That Can’t Be, (1966) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - About Will Campbell; Little Rock-Ten years Later, (1967) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Last People Between the Lakes, (1968) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - A Report on New Educational Enterprises, (1971) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Special to American Report, Doctorates, (1971) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Healing of a Nation by David Loye (Book review); An Overview of Governance in Public Black Education with Particular Emphasis on the Public Black Institutions in Florida, South Carolina, North Carolina, Virginia, Alabama and Louisiana, (1971) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Model Programs for Cultural Pluralism in Higher Education, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Opryland; Columbia, South Carolina-A Southern Center Where There May Still Be Time; Ole Miss, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Preliminary Information on Public Higher Education in South Carolina; Down to Now by Pat Walters (Book Review); Black Colleges, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Grandparents; Tennessee Politics, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - What’s Right with Busing, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Alright, Everybody Off the Bus, WLAC Radio Talk, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Teachers, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The School Desegregation Act of, 1972 (1972) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Desegregation, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hayes Mizell, School Board Member; Wey’s Way; Infant Education, (1972) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Facing the Lions by Tom Wicker and The Last of the Southern Girls by Willie Morris (Book Reviews); Head Start; Vouchers; CUTE-Cooperative Urban Teacher Education, (1973) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Interviews with Dr. Leon Kamin; Farm School; Memorandum to Jean Fairfax; Katallgete; Being a Southerner in the New South, (1973) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - But Does One Know When to Quit Hustling His Book?; Transforming Trash in Nashville; Mississippi Conversations, (1973-1974) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Fisk, (1974) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - The Deep South States of America by Neal R. Pierce (Book Review); This Little Piggie Cried “Wee! Wee! Wee!”; South (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Reflections of a (lower-case) humanist; Cities (Nashville); Southern Governmental Monitoring Project; The Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education (Report), (1974) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ending Discrimination in Higher Education: A Report from Ten States, (1974) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hello, Boston, This Is Little Rock Calling; The Man Who Cried Impeachment First; Minority Policemen: How Many Are There?, (1974) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Can Separate Be Equal?; The View from the Hills, (1974-1975) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - My Turn; Address to the Queens College Book and Author Luncheon, (1975) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Equality of Access to postsecondary Education, (1975) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Word Crisis; Psychology-Dartmouth, (1975) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Education by Crisis; Looking for Jimmy; Back to Basics, (1976) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Patty Hearst; Inequality; Teachers; Pride, (1976) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - John Buffington; Carter and the Southern Issue; Final Tribute to the Good Ole Boys, (1976) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Minorities and the Media; Land-Use Planning in North Nashville; Sue Alston; Tip Top Inn, (1976) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - South Can Preserve Its Heritage By Balancing Growth; Merger of Black, White Universities Ordered in Nashville; New Dissension Flares in Tennessee System; Head Elementary School Has All the Ingredients, (1977) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Humanities; A Chance to Learn by Meyer Weinberg (Book Review), (1977) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Reflections on Utopianism; Speech at Virginia Tech; Ruth Harriet Jacobs, (1977) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Changing Agenda of Higher Education; Speech to Trident 2000, Charleston; Speech to Charlotte Historic Properties Commission, (1977) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Apples; New South; Carter Country; Squatters’ Rights; Starting Over, (1977) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - The Seeds of Racial Justice (A review of In Search of the Silent South by Morton Sosna, (1978) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Days of Heroism and Shame (A review of My Soul Is Rested by Howell Raines; A Pervasive Acceptance of Segregation; The Issues Medical Schools Have Ignored, (1978) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - A One-Year Hitch in the Professoriate; After A Year of Teaching At VPI, A Writer Calls It Quits, (1978) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Winner Names the Age by Lillian Smith (Book Review); Koinonia Housing; Libraries, (1978) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Moving; Shaggy-dog Stories; Watermelon Wine: the Spirit of Country Music by Faye Gaillard (Book Review), (1978) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - The Albatross Lives; Letters from Rhodesia, (1978) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - A Gentlemen’s Fight; Going Back Would Be Unthinkable, (1979) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Fantasy; The Second Coming by Walker Percy (Book Review); American Dreams: Lost and Found by Studs Terkel (Book Review), (1980) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - A Pilgrim’s Progress (Speech at Rugby, Tennessee (October 5, 1980 and October 5, 2005); Addie Ledford (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Words as an Endangered Species; Metro School Tax, (1981) (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - The Match, And How to Make It, (1981) (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Gene Graham; Policy Comes Home; New Harmony; Wordsmiths, (1982) (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Can We Save the Schools?; Pack Up Your Troubles; The Lost Art of Listening; My Son, On the Right Track; A Lock of Ages Opens to a Book Called Generations, (1982) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Book Reviews---There Is a River by Vincent Harding; Hearts and Minds by Harry S. Ashmore; The Glad River by Will Campbell, (1983) (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - The Push Is On; Country Ham and Beaten Biscuits; Julius Wayland; Nashoba Experiment, (1983) (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Eighty Years of Respect for Berea; An Interview with John Egerton; “Progress” Is Wonderful Only If You Can Afford It, (1984) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Olympics “Big Show” A Spectacle Not To Be Missed; Capital Punishment a Legal Killing Which Has No Place in Our Society, (1984) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Appalachia: The Politics of History; I Am What I Am; Barbecue, (1984) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Southern Voices, Old and New; Will the Earth Endure?; Morrissey Photographs, (1984) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Book Reviews---Southern Progressivism: The Reconciliation of Progress and Tradition by Dewey W. Grantham; The Good War by Studs Terkel; Tell About the South: The Southern Rage to Explain by Fred Hobson; The Kidwells: A Family Odyssey by Dwayne E. Walls, (1984) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Speaking of History; A Determined Wordsmith; The Bottom Line; The Second Coming of Watson Brown, (1985) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Gone with the Ivy: A Biography of Vanderbilt University by Paul Conkin (Book Review), (1985) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Daniel Kimmis; Wentworth Caldwell; The Greeks: Coming in Through the Kitchen; A Writer Turns to Farming, (1986) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Kate Jackson; Bobbie Ann Mason, (1986) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Book Reviews---Forty Acres and a Goat by Will Campbell; Looking for Hogeye by Roy Reed; Vera Cruz by Rosalind Wright; Myth, Media, and the Southern Mind by Stephen A Smith, (1986) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Pilgrim’s Progress: The Travels of Duncan Hines; A Latter-day Immigrant in America; Looking Back: From Miami to Milwaukee, (1986) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Possum on Terrace (John Popham), (1987) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Weems Book: The Land, The People, The Homeplace, The Workplace, (1987) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Book Collecting; John Egerton on Writing; A Past Remembered: A Collection of Antebellum Homes in Davidson County by Paul Clements (Book Review), (1987) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Klan Basher; When “Reason” Reigned in Kansas; Women, Food, and Southern Culture; Politics and Food, (1988) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Robert Allen; The Lost First Edition of Upton Sinclair’s ‘The Jungle’, Edited with an Introduction by Gene DeGruson, (1988) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - New Southern Cookbooks Owe Much to Dull, Brown; About Men and Cooking; Kentucky Book Fair, (1988) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Files 18 through 25 are Food Articles for “Southern Food”, October, 1988 to December, 1989 (Box 5)
  - October 2, 1988-November 6, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - November 13, 1988-December 25, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - January 1, 1989-February 26, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - March 5, 1989-April 30, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - May 7, 1989-June 25, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - July 2, 1989-August 27, 2989 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - September 1, 1989-October 29, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - November 5, 1989-December 31, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Commanding Presence; The South’s Last Stand; Myles Horton (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Book Reviews---Covenant by Al Clayton; The Encyclopedia of Southern Culture, Edited by William Ferris and Charles Wilson; American Years by Harold Sinclair, (1989) (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Book Reviews---The Dream Long Deferred by Faye Galliard; The Rest of the Dream by Wade Hall; A Turn in the South by V.S. Naipul, (1989) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Roots of Southern Food; Call It a Southern Revival; Barbecue; A Nashville Memory; Blue Plate Heaven; Deja Vu All Over Again, (1990) (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Book Reviews: A Foxfire Christmas: Appalachian Memories and Traditions, Editor-Eliot Wigginton; The Secret Diary of Mikhail Gorbachev by Faye Galliard; Delta Time: A Journey Through Mississippi by Tony Dunbar, (1990) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Book Reviews: Spring Hill, Tennessee by Tom T. Hall; The Long Haul by Myles Horton, with Judith and Herbert Kohl, (1990) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Dixie Diner; Merchants; Old Restaurants, (1990) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Promised Land by Nicholas Lemann (Book Review); Aloha, Y’all!; People’s Houses; The Pre-Brown South; Highlander in the Thirties, (1991-1994) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Generations by Richard Fielder, a Script Based on John Egerton’s Book, Generations, (1992) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Striving for Equilibrium; In Pursuit of the Perfect Fried Chicken; The Immortality of Fried Chicken, (1992-1995) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Redeye: A Western by Clyde Egerton (Book Review); The South As An American Problem; James Still: In His World; Bob Sykes Barbecue, (1994-1996) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - A Southern Sense of Place; Promises, Promises; Volunteer Forty-Niners: Tennesseans and the California Gold Rush by Walter Durham (Book Review), (1997) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Unfinished Business; Kentucky: A Guide to the Bluegrass State- Compiled and Written by the Federal Writers’ Project of the Works Program Administration for the State of Kentucky, 1939 (Book Review), (1997) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - His Own Drummer; Notes from the Hot Bread Zone; The Gravity of Segregation, (2000-2004) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The People vs. George Bush; The Endurance of Southern Food; Writer of the South (2 copies), (2000-2004) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - The Literary Patriot (2 copies); As God Is My Witness, I’ll Never Go Hungry Again, (2006-2007) (Box 6, Folder 12)